[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hi this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio and today I'm
talking to Jonathan Horvath he's the
owner of the zbit physical Access
Control Systems consultancy and the
author of an open- Source implementation
of the open supervised device protocol
he has over 25 years of experience in
the physical access control system space
and he got to start answering support
calls at Lenell systems Jonathan welcome
to software engineering radio hello
Jeremy glad to be here I think a lot of
our audience they may have interacted
with physical Access Control Systems but
they probably don't actually know what
that means so could you start by
explaining what that means so physical
access control is monitoring and giving
access to and securing physical spaces
if you compare it to logical access
control with identity management it's
does a lot of the same things but it's
in the physical domain so you have a lot
of the same Concepts you have
authentication authorization and audit
so when you go up to a secure area you
want to authenticate yourself typically
with a card or nowadays lot lot of
people use mobile phones or even
Biometrics like a fingerprint and then
there's a check to see if you're
authorized to enter that space and like
I said it's typically through a door but
there's other ways of accessing in a
physical space and then once you've been
authorized then you audit or if you're
not authorized it'll audit that
transaction physical Access Control also
encompasses other security modern and
aspects to those physical spaces so a
lot of physical Access Control software
systems will include like video
surveillance uh contacts if you have a
analog contact that's connected to a
window and someone opens the window you
might want to monitor that and control
points some that you would regularly use
a control point for is to unlock a door
a door strike so to manage and to
effectively secure those spaces that's
all in the realm of physical access
control and so you talked about
authentication and authorization so
Authentication
is determining who you are and that's
based off of the token like you said it
could be a card or a mobile phone and
then the authorization that's deciding
whether or not you're supposed to be
able to get into that door or that
vehicle Turn Style that place you're
trying to enter is that right yes
correct and you mentioned I believe did
you say control Point could you explain
what you meant by that it deals with
everything within the physical space
that you need to secure so there's times
when you need to perform an action or a
lot of times the control points are
relays and like I said typical one is to
unlock a door there's a door strike
electronic door strike and it's
magnetized and you need to provide
control of that door when someone's
authorized to enter that door and other
examples could be a gate to go into a
parking space and there's many other
things you want to control depending on
the situation you need to perform an
action on so the control point in the
example of for example a vehicle gate
that somebody drives their car up to
they scan their card to get in to the
parking lot and the control point would
be the physical thing that you need to
control to cause the gate arm to open or
something like that exactly you kind of
gave some examples of ways people might
see this in their day-to-day they might
see it and entering their hotel room or
entering their office building going
into a parking lot things like that what
are the physical components of that
system like there must be something to
read the credential there must be some
kind of software piece in the background
maybe you can walk us through so
building up through the layers or the
flow it starts off with identifying who
you are so a lot of times or it
typically has been a card so you carry
everybody who when you start at a
company the first one of the first
things you get is the company C and that
gives you access to the door at a hotel
room one of the first things you get is
your hotel Key and you get into your
hotel room if you are signed up for a
parking garage downtown in some City
when you pay your monthly due the first
thing you get is a parking garage card
so that's the typical way of gaining
access this has been changing in the
past 10 or 15 years with the
introduction of biometrics so now people
with higher secured areas there's
fingerprint more traditional I'm
thinking about it is you know a keypad
you know some places that instead of
giving out cards they give you a PIN
code and you use that PIN code and
that's something you know and not
necessarily something you have there's
multi Factor authentication like in The
Logical access control so you might use
a combination of a card and a
fingerprint or a card and pin for higher
secured areas and then the next part is
the actual reader who takes that card
pin keypad biometric and it's the
physical interface between the person
and the physical Access Control software
system those readers we'll get into it
later we can have a discussion but those
readers is the end point in the system
so a lot of times those readers just
pass through the information but with
the chips becoming cheaper and more
economical to actually do some decision-
making that and have some intelligence
at that reader and then once the reader
collects that information either be a
pin card number biometric fingerprint
template it transmit that to a panel so
it's an access control panel that's
usually in a lock cabinet that's secured
so it doesn't go right to the server
host these are Life Safety Systems so a
lot required to have a separate panel
that's been hardened and that usually
has like a backup like a local battery
hooked up to it so that it's a power out
it can still continue to allow people to
enter and active physical spaces and it
has a 12vt looks like a little car
battery maybe like a quarter of the size
but it sits there and the panel is just
what you would like a fire panel or any
other it's just basically it looks like
a motherboard and it has a bunch of
inputs and outputs relays and some
comport that hooks up to your readers
and other Downstream panels you one
panel might manage like 128 doors and
they have sub panel pels hooked up for
all those doors they don't go into one
panel they daisy chain them down with
sub panels for readers and other iOS and
then that hooks up to a host system so
you have all these panels within your
physical access control system you have
a large Enterprise you might have
thousands of those panels and they all
have to be managed and updated with new
credentials new access levels new time
zones different actions or workflows
depending on various input or events
that happen and this is where I'm mostly
involved with is actual development of
that software that runs on the server
and the adoption has been increasing
like on the cloud that manages all these
panels so that gives you kind of a
highlevel architectural overview of when
you're looking at a physical access
control system like I said there's four
components you have the credential the
physical credential or and like I said
that credential could be a fingerprint
or Biometrics but and then you have the
reader the endpoint the panel and that
panel can typically is the one that
making the decision whether you're
authorized or not it has a full database
if it's disconnected from the whole
system it it can make all the decisions
locally on premise and then you have the
host software that manages all the
panels within your system so if I break
it down a little bit the person let's
say they go to their office building
there's a card reader on the outside
they present their credential you had
mentioned that the card reader is almost
like a pass through kind of thing it
gets the card number or the information
identifying you from the card it sends
that to the panel and then the panel you
said has its own local database that
decides whether or not you get into the
building and if it decides that you do
that panel is physically wired to what
you were referring to as control points
so the door strike that unlocks the door
the panel is connected to that and so
it'll make the decision to let you in
and take care of that m that last part
you mentioned the server software or the
software that's connecting to these
panels I'm guessing that's updating
these panels databases that's sort of
the source of Truth in terms of who's
supposed to get in and who's not yeah
that is the source of truth that is the
interaction from The Operators of the
system is through that host system that
host system in our industry Windows is
pretty prevalent so on a Windows Server
some of the software I work with is old
school client server so you still have
like Wind forms or uh other traditional
Windows uh UI elements or it could be a
web base uh UI and that makes the update
so you enroll if a new employee comes in
you go to a badge in station and you
take a photo and you store that in the
host system and you type in the first
and last name maybe some other
identifying information and you issue
them a card and that card is associated
with that new employee or you go into
the host system and say I want to give
this person to all employee doors and
those employee doors if it's a large
campus might be connected to many panels
so the software host system needs to
decide where this information needs to
be sent what information needs to be
sent and it figures out through drivers
you know Jonathan Horvath is starting at
company Acme his credential needs to go
down and then this credential
specifically will have access to these
doors and there's time zones involved to
scheduling so maybe he has access to
these doors during business hours
certain doors maybe other doors he has
access all hours depending on the
security of those areas and other doors
obviously they're not associated with so
I'll get denied access to maybe that
super secret government section of the
building where only certain employees
could go in or the Executive Suite or
something of that nature and so when you
mentioned the drivers that would be the
software that the server software needs
to know how to communicate with the
panels correct it's typically called a
driver I can give you a little further
background when I first started access
control systems were proprietary and
they were all all of these components
that we talked about earlier were
developed and sold as one system so you
would have a card you would have a
reader you would have an axess panel and
you would have way back would actually
go right to the control panel and
program that but that doesn't scale as
the assistance became larger and you
would create a custom protocol between
the panel and the host system and
actually to this day a lot of that is
proprietary so each panel has their own
protocol or some of the newer ones have
a rest API and you would have to
interface with that so you would send
down as information was entered into the
host system the host system would
determined with each panel what data
records need to go down to that panel
and it would update that panel with the
appropriate credentials the appropriate
access levels appropriate schedules and
you could do other local things there
like if at certain times at night it
would lock the door maybe if it's a main
entrance it would unlock the door during
business hours unlock so you would have
some decision making done at that panel
and as we progress and some of the newer
Access Control Systems no longer is
single source for all those components
the Software System might talk to
different panels with different
protocols so that driver even in the
same system so there might be two or
three manufactured panels in there and
each one has to have a separate driver
much like a computer so even though I'm
doing the same function each one has
some nuanced and you have to translate
your intended actions for each one to
that particular manufacturer more and
more these components are no longer a
unified single Source from one
manufacturer now you have a lot of
diversity and you have to take an
account of having different cards from
different manufacturers readers from
another manufacturer a panel from yet
another manufacturer and a whole system
software system from yet another
manufacturer this has become more and
more common this is one of the
challenges in the physical Access
Control currently which is interesting
because this is something that's been
solved for many years within the it and
software development of having standard
protocols but this is something actually
that's fairly new in these components
we've been talking about within the
physical access control space which is
great for someone who's been developing
software in this industry for a long
time to kind of losing my hair over many
you know many years trying to have to
deal with these proprietary systems and
very limited what you could do creating
Solutions because of the proprietar
implementations now that it's opening up
to standards and open protocols this is
really has made my ability to provide
solutions to my clients much easier the
part that is proprietary or not
standardized it sounds like is the
panels right my main pain point right
now is the proprietary drivers that we
were talking about between the host
system and the panel that's still very
proprietary there is one open standard
but it's not really followed right now
there hasn't been really a market push
to open that up but we'll get into some
of my other areas that have the other
links between the other lower level
communication those have been coming
standardized so I'm hoping once those
become more mature we can work back up
to where I spend most of my time with
the software development of the host
system and so since there isn't a
standard way of communicating between
the host system and the panels do you
see any kind of common ways that they
build these interfaces is it usually
some kind of proprietary TCP interface
or are they using HTTP I'm just curious
what those typically look like so
there's common terms you know you have
credential you have access level you
have time zone or schedule so you have
some common domain terms but it's all
over the place everyone is really a
snowflake and unique and it's how it
implements some have raw TCP very
archaic commands that are a bunch of
numbers you look at it you have no idea
if you didn't have the API guide it just
is a series of numbers maybe with some
text in there and then there's all the
way up to a nice rest API you know a
little more modern rest API and
everything in between but yeah it's all
over the board what you encounter it
sounds like when you were mentioning
needing the documentation and things
like this is this the sort of thing
where you can't really integrate with
these panels unless you have support
from these vendors yeah correct so
because it's proprietary a lot of times
you don't have public access to a lot of
these apis so you have to sign either
sign an agreement and it's very
restricted so a lot of times I will work
through a client and the client has
access to it and because I'm working
through them I'll have access to it but
I have to be very careful about I can't
share it with anyone it's a very closed
system and for the project I'm working
on is fine and you can get support but
if you want to go beyond that or if you
think of ideas of oh I know I got this
panel and I want to add this new
function ity to it there are some
roadblocks to doing that a lot of times
you have to go through the manufacturer
and get their blessing a lot of
traditional web Based Services you know
you have a great idea and you go build
it and you know have all these open
protocols like HTML and JavaScript and
use WordPress or you know whatever great
Frameworks react or whatever out there
and you build your great idea what I
work in my domain everything's limited
because whatever you do needs to be
expressed in some physical form so you
have these Gatekeepers of manufacturer
who build these physical products that
you need to interact with be it the
panel reader or credentials and if they
don't give the blessing you even though
you have this great idea you can't
really go anywhere with it you have to
work with that which makes it tough
sometimes but it makes it interesting I
mean I really do enjoy the aspect of
building something and having the
physical manifestation of what you've
done in my office here I have all kinds
of readers and device and stuff and it's
I know it gets me excited when I program
something and I see it physically work
the way I'm supposed to work right next
to me and then you know you go into
buildings and stuff and you see how all
these devices working you you know and
you know you have a impact on making
sure they're working properly it sounds
like when you think about for example
iot devices there are standards or
message formats like mqtt or if you are
working with cameras
it's pretty common for there to be an
rtsp Stream So a standard way of
streaming the video a standard codec but
on the physical Access Control side it
sounds like there really isn't that kind
of ecosystem yeah no there not isn't
really I mean I went off on my own and
did my own Consulting business is that's
one of the main passions and drivers I
had moving forward is try to introduce
some Open Standards so a lot of my work
is Building Solutions that are based off
of Open standards and there is a
movement within the industry to embrace
these new standards in my opinion it's
one of those evolution of the industry
that will help grow the market so it's
pretty exciting now to be involved with
these various open standard work groups
and conferences and see that the
industry is finally embracing these it
does take a while though unlike
traditional software engineering even if
we had all the standards mapped out and
everybody agreed to them there is a long
cycle time to implement them because
we're talking about physical Hardware so
it's not oh you know we got a new update
to the standard and or we want to
implement the standard you can't just
push a button and do your automated
builds and automated deployments and
deploy to your host system you need to
have all the hardware in place and those
Hardwares need to be updated so you
might have to go and if they're older
Hardware you might have to replace them
if you have newer Hardware that may need
to have an updated firmware so so you
might have depending on the firmware
version you might actually have to
visibly go and connect to the reader and
update the firmware on them to support
this new standard same thing with the
panels a lot of the panels you can do
firmware updates luckily now but you
still have to push those out and you
have to coordinate with your security
operations center because you have
downtime so there's a lot of things you
got to take into consideration that may
not you know in the pure virtual logical
world you don't need to take account for
and even the credentials you know I was
in a conference earlier this week where
we're looking to standardize on the
credential protocols between the
credential and the reader and you know
that's for a large company or even a
small one with limited resources you
know it's a big undertaking to replace
all those credentials or you know you
can't just rebadge everybody especially
these days where everybody's not coming
to the office you know being able to get
badges to everybody is a big undertaking
and the cost of the just the badges and
having employees go to you know making
sure the badges get securely to the
employees you can't just maybe you
probably don't want to mail them out
there's a lot of logistical overhead on
deploying a new standard so there's a
lot more considerations that need to be
taken into account if you update to a
new badge technology a lot of times you
have to what they call it bridge if you
have a thousand readers which is a
moderately sized system you'll have some
readers that had the new technology or
the new standard and you have some that
don't but people don't want to carry
three or four badges for all these
different and knowing which badge to use
at what reader so you have badges with
multiple Technologies on them you'll
have readers that can read multiple
Technologies and you have panels that
can interpret those multiple
Technologies so you have uh these
backward compatibilities with this roll
out that could take you a few years as
you replace the hardware or update the
firmware or Inu new card formats so yeah
there's a lot of thought and
consideration needs to be have for
rolling out new technology and new
standards so I thought we could kind of
walk through a little bit deeper into
each of the components one of the things
you mentioned is the host software or
the server software that's talking to
the panels and how it was typically a
Windows application I was wondering if
you had any insight into why that was so
actually the company you mentioned in my
BIOS LEL systems probably had a lot to
do with that so when I started out in
Access Control it wasn't like I was
growing up and I wanted to do physical
control I like computers and hacked
around and played with the old PCS and
did some Linux uni stuff when I was in
college and I was looking for a job and
just so happened a physical Access
Control startup named Lenell systems was
not too far for me a few miles away and
got a job there and it was one of the
first a control systems before well now
most of them like I said you would
either program directly on the p panel
you would hook up a computer using a
cereal comport if you remember the old
cereal and we still use those a lot in
our industry but You' have the old
cereal poured on your computer and you
would hook it up there and you would
type in some arcade commands and you
would do it manually and then in the 80s
and 90s you would have Unix base but
they were very expensive you would have
to have a expensive Unix computer and
they were still command line mostly done
through command line and they were
clunky and you kind of had to had like a
Access Control Guru to go in there and
Lenell systems they one of the first
companies and they became very popular
and spearheaded this to support a
graphical interface and one of the first
big customers on now was Microsoft and
they started early on betting the
company on the popularity of uh Windows
NT the precursor to your modern Windows
system and they became very successful
they come to become one of the top
physical acction control companies
within the industry a few years later so
that kind of drove the adoption of
Windows as a physical access control
system for host and like I said once a
company gets established within the
industry it's very hard to replace them
because of the hardware considerations I
was talking about earlier so that was
the first widely deployed ax control
system that was very user friendly was
through windows in the late 90s and
early 2000s and it was mostly on premise
too because a lot of times especially
early on they were on a a separate
Network there was no internet access
this is a secure system and to ensure no
outside access a lot of times these
systems didn't have any internet access
so internet even though these the LEL
systems started out in the dot area
where a lot of stuff was going online
and on the web a lot of the customers
didn't want their physical access
control system online so a lot of it was
all of it was on premise until the past
10 years or so so windows made the most
sense it was the most economical way of
deploying a non premise system so that
that's a quick background now there's a
lot more diversity you have cloud-based
systems I'm sure written in various
languages you have Linux that are
typically black boxes so you buy a hose
system that's basically you know a box
and you put it in your and you can mount
it in your server room and there's just
a web interface so there's some of those
that have come up over the years but
just a momentum of when the Windows
systems became popular in the early
2000s we still riding that momentum and
slowly they're being replaced but like I
said there's it's a common theme these
Technologies are hard to replace once
they get embedded they have a shelf life
of 10 20 years yeah so it seems like
more of a result of when this industry
started cuz I I do recall that yeah late
'90s early 2000 a lot of people were
still running server software on Windows
and it seems like the last 10 15 years
there's been this shift to where the
majority is probably on Linux now so
maybe if this industry had really come
up later then maybe it wouldn't have
been Windows yeah exactly it's just the
timing ideally with these Open Standards
that I've been promoted and advocating
for it'll be easier to keep up with
technology as a comes out that would be
the hope and that's one of the Sal
pictures I commonly give to clients once
these physical action Control Systems
started to connect to the network and
the internet taking your time to update
stuff and kind of resting on your
laurels as far as up doing security
patches and all that it was s kind of a
comfort and it didn't seem to be as
important to keep up with stuff because
you know we're on a separate Network it
there's no outside access so can I kind
of you still do updates and everything
but since we're not connected anything
there was kind of a security blanket you
know that we didn't need to be concerned
so much about interconnectivity and
standards and all that and that has
changed most of these systems are now
being connected to their corporate
Network and even now with the
cloud-based systems are connected to the
internet so standards are becoming more
and more important as part of the whole
physical action control system because
it's no longer an isolated system it is
part of a larger Enterprise system or a
larger interconnected online system so
that's forc and and it is obviously is
more involved now because it's part of
their it system so they demand like
what's going on underneath the hood what
protocols are you using can we interface
with those how do we interface with
those so hiding behind the curtain is no
longer acceptable for new deployments
and existing deployments are being
reviewed and questioned to why these
Legacy systems still have these
restrictions
yeah that makes sense like you were
saying before it didn't matter as much
because you figure oh somebody has to
physically be here and connect to our
Network these cabinets are locked and
these host systems are disconnected from
the rest of the network there was a
sense that some of these security
shortcomings were okay because you know
as long as there's no outside access I
was uh thinking as you were talking I
remember watching a movie and there was
a heist going on in an actual site of
where I program the access control
system and I was so worried like they
were looking to figure out how to get in
there and you know they they were
talking about the security system and
how they're going to circumvent it and I
was so worried that they were going to
hack it like the traditional hack where
you know you go in and you find a
vulnerability in the security system and
I was actually you know felt it within
my gut like I was nervous about this you
know it's make believe it's a movie has
nothing to do but it seemed kind of
personal to me because they were trying
to get into a security system that I was
involved with building and what you were
saying earlier what they ended up doing
was they got one of the guards and they
compromised him I don't know took him to
a strip club or something and took his
badge and used his badge to get actually
get into the Data Center and they put a
little bugger on there and they had
physical access into the physical system
into the physical access control system
or whatever and the video system so once
they put the little thing on the network
cable then they had access to everything
because they were physically inside the
building inside the server room and I
breathe a side relief like oh they
didn't hack my system they actually
physically went in and there's nothing
you can do at that point so once you
physically get into the data center or
to the server there's not much you can
do you know if you're not detected and
you're in there you can put sniffers on
there and you can do all kinds of stuff
that you know once you have physical
access to something you know all bets
are off you had mentioned that there are
a lot of vulnerabilities that continue
to exist I wonder if you can talk about
some of those the most interesting one
this is brings up the conference I was
in earlier this week so credentials
continually have issues of being able to
clone them or replicate them it's been
an ongoing issue for as long as I can
remember credentials started with mag
Stripes it was one of the first things
that repl me essentially we're replacing
lock and key on doors and the mag stripe
and I'm assuming most people are
familiar with it I mean it's kind of
dated these days but even new credit
cards still have that mag stripe on the
back and and the mag stripe essentially
is is an encoded bytes uh I'm really
dating myself when I started with
computers we used to store our programs
on cassette tapes and it's the same
concept obviously those are easy to
clone I mean you can take that mag
stripe and when you present it to a
reader in the old days it would just
take those bites and transmit them to
the panel if I got a hold your badge I
could take that mag stripe and swipe it
into a my own reader and get those bites
and then create a new magstripe with the
same exact bites like you were you like
I said I'm dating myself but the old
cassette tape you could take a cassette
tape and put one of those dual copiers
and you could put another cassette tape
there and you can make a copy of it so
it was really easy to clone and mag
stpes are so they got replaced by I
think called procs that's the
contactless card that everybody's
familiar with where you tap the card on
the reader so the initial procs were you
know you looking back and they were very
insecure so basically it took those
magstripe bites and you put them in a
magnetic ring of wires and when you
present it to a reader it would energize
them and it would send out unique bit
array and send that from the reader up
to the panel through unencrypted oneway
wires so that was called wegan and
completely unencrypted in the old days
it was kind of hard to clone those you
would need to have a lot of expensive
equipment it was just clunky nowadays as
scenes got smaller to clone them is
super easy you can because they're
contactless in some ways the Mad Card is
a little more secure because you
actually have to physically take the
card and swipe it the contact list you
could walk up to someone and if you have
the right equipment you know you could
be like within a few feet and you can
capture that card and energize it and
get the bit array and then you can
create your own card and you can be that
person so that's wegan and to this day
there's fortunately there's still
deployments with wean going out and
there's obviously exists like I said
this stuff has shelf life of decades so
there's still systems out there using
this fairly easy to clone not very
secure card and the past 15 or so years
there smart cards uh typically you know
the chip on the card a lot of the credit
cards have and they have keys and they
encrypt and decrypt the communications
between the card and the reader and it's
similar to credit cards you can do
contact list you can do the tap or you
can put the card in and it'll make
contact to the chip and the initial
implementation of those did were finding
that they had some significant security
issues the initial ones you have to
remember these readers initially were
pass through devices so they were very
cheap to produce they weren't really
doing anything they were just taking in
the wegan days they were just basically
taking the same transmission between the
card and the reader and just continuing
up to the panel there was no protocol it
was just basically extending the reach
of the panel to receive the credential
you know the weeken information from the
card there was no back and forth the
smart card they didn't want to put a lot
of new smart into these readers because
there was an expectation that these were
still going to be cheap so what they did
is they did a shared key you know a
symmetrical key between the card and the
reader so they' have a shared private
key which was better than wegan you know
you had two-way Communications between
the card and the reader and it was
encrypted it was hard to clone you
couldn't clone unless you had the actual
private key the problem in they just did
a presentation at Defcon a few days ago
is that if someone figures out or able
to get get that shared key they can
easily clone a card because once you
have the shared key you can decrypt that
card and if you know about it like I
said earlier it's hard to do updates you
would have to replace all the cards and
update all the readers with a new key to
mitigate that security issue so that
becomes very expensive so what we're
looking at what's being attempted to do
now and this like I said requires
readers to be updated with much more
smarts than they've been traditionally
been manufactured to have is do
asymmetrical Keys pki similar to like an
SSH login you would have a private key
stored in a secure element with either
within the smart card or mobile phone
and that's not shared it's Unique for
every credential holder every credential
and then that credential is validated
using the public key that's transmitted
and if a hacker somehow figured out the
private key on the card they would just
have access to that one card it really
minimizes your potential security risk
to just that card instead of the whole
system so that's kind of the next and
this is what I've been involved with is
I don't know if you want to get into but
this is already been implemented in the
government obviously there's a lot of
very secure government facilities
there's lot of proprietary solutions
that were for commercial but in the
government there's a
identification regulation standard
called PIV personal identification that
is widespread through all the government
agency and that's based on what I was
just talking about a pki
infrastructure with stored private key
on the credential so it's a very good
way of thinking where the physical
access industry needs to go and we would
have done that years ago but we have all
this Hardware we need to replace I mean
it's one of those obvious things if
you're doing software development or an
IT person technician or administrator
but and I think a lot of people in our
industry realize this but I'm glad we
talked about that earlier you have to
appreciate the amount of resources are
needed and the time needed to do the
switch over but it's good to see there's
progress being made and on know flip
side too there's some areas where you
got to secure this area and you need to
do pki or PIV and you know a government
installation that has top secret
information or sensitive but there's
other areas where it's not as important
you know that pretty good security that
it's not dead simple to get in you know
and another thing that's changed is the
ability like I said the old wean stuff
at first seemed kind of secure because
the equipment to do the cloning was very
expensive and very clumb brome like you
would know if someone like was walking
up and next to you cuz they would
probably have a big you know backpack
with bunch of devices like it would
stand out but there's newer devices out
now that you can put in your pocket and
you can stand next to someone and be
able to clone it so as technology gets
better even these kind of half-baked
solutions that were fairly secure become
much less secure as the ability to clone
them becomes much easier and much less
technically know how to be able to pull
it off now there's devices you can buy
off at Amazon that can do a lot of
things for cloning with a lot of the
badges that are out there now are there
any specific things to look for like
let's say you check into your hotel is
there an obvious way to tell oh this is
something that I could easily clone yeah
there are so there's a device called The
Flipper and basically it has a bunch of
technology that I actually have on my
desk right now but it made into a
consumable product that allows you to
hack into physical Access Control
Systems and it has an NFC chip on it and
wegan reader and some other interfaces
and yeah I mean if you had to flip her
and you put your hotel badge key to it
it could tell you if it's you know has a
technology on there that is easily
cracked and then I don't know what you
could do when you find out I mean you
already have a reservation at a hotel
you're kind of stuck with it I mean I
don't get too far into the weeds with
that stuff I know there's people who go
in you know they have their flipper and
they go and check but what can you
really do at that moment you already
have a reservation to stay there that
night you're not going to go around to
different hotels and find the one that
actually has a secure badge I guess it's
good knowledge to have but like I said
personally I don't really get into like
nitpicking each individual
implementation I try to provide tools
and advocate for Open Standards are
inherently secure so that they're
available and hopefully anybody who's
concerned about Security will be able to
implement that in a cost-effective
fashion yeah I suppose in that example
the assumption would be once you check
out of your hotel that card probably the
access gets revoked or changed so you
couldn't just go back you know a week
later and go into the same room uh it
depends a lot of times they do reprogram
those cards but they might use the same
identifier on the card depending on how
they Implement so the identifier card
the reader might just have one unique
identifier like this reader if your card
presents this identifier it'll gain give
you access so maybe they erase it when
you bring it back but then they'll just
reprogram with the same exact identifier
when the next guest comes in so if I
have that let's say room 301 and I
figure out what that ident because those
readers on those doors aren't Uplink to
anything so they only know how to allow
access access to one particular
identifier well traditionally I mean
maybe it could be newer readers that can
get updates but the cheaper readers will
only allow a certain card number to gain
access and I think all the front desk is
doing is erasing that card and then
reprogram it for the other room with
that identifier so once you get a room
you're able to clone like I said room
301 that will always work it's not like
that locks getting updated with a
different identifier for each person
coming in each customer that's coming in
sleeping for that night oh interesting
so the reader itself knows that I'm
reader 301 and as long as you give me a
card that says it's 4301 it may just
open it may not be tied to like you were
saying a panel or a backend server
system to even check yeah so one thing I
didn't get into so the the checkin of
authorization can be done at just about
every part of this system we talked
about the four parts it could be done on
their credential so there are
credentials out there that because smart
cards the newer ones more expensive ones
have you know they have storage on them
so you could store all your access
decision-making Ray on that card and as
you present there's called mesh access
control so you as you present it gets
updates on where people have access to
to which reader so and then also cell
phones a cell phone if you present it to
a door it could go up to the cloud and
make access decisions and based on what
door you present it to and say oh you
have access to the door and then it was
some secret key or some type encrypted
thing to the door to unlock it so the
authorization decision could be made at
the credential could be at the reader so
if the reader is not connected to a
panel and this is when you brought up
hotel rooms this is typically the case
it's an offline reader the reader
doesn't have any wired connections it's
just on that door there's no wire that
goes to a panel and because these are
battery powered typically if they have
Wi-Fi on them they're not continually
getting updates through Wi-Fi otherwise
those batteries will be sapped of their
power pretty quickly so ideally a lot of
times if they're Wi-Fi they might only
communicate back to the host system or
panel like once a day there's some low
frequency lower powered ways of
communicating that can allow realtime
updates but usually they're proprietary
but there's things like some of the home
automation like zigg I think matter and
that can go over Wireless for low power
and Z I have zwave locks at my house so
those can do real time but still you got
to be careful on what how much traffic
you do because if you're constantly
updating especially with a high traffic
area those batteries will get sapped
pretty quickly but the technolog is
getting better and better so they can do
more and more of those offline locks or
locks that are wireless and then
majority of especially traditional is
the reader is hooked up to the panel and
the panel does the authorization has its
own local database and that should be
locked in a locked cabinet that's in a
secure room so the whole system
typically does not and should not be
making those decisions just because
they're not as reliable the closer you
can do it to the actual location the
more secure it is the more layers you go
through there's more points of security
vulnerabilties so usually if you're in a
host system you're going through
multiple layers and once the traffics is
traversed person through the internet or
through a corporate Network there's more
opportunity to intercept that and do
some man- in the-middle hacking or
intercepting yeah and I I suppose if the
host system is more commonly getting
moved to the cloud if you were relying
on that to make the decision that let
somebody in if let's say you are going
into a office building and the internet
is down then it's like you can't get in
the building which seems not great if it
comes to life safety issu so you want to
make that decision making as close to
the end point as possible so that if you
lose connectivity you have an emergency
you want to try to find ways to make the
access control system still operational
and be able to make decisions regardless
of what's going on outside of your
immediate area so you mentioned you've
done work with the host systems so it
sounds like we were talking about
earlier how usually that's a Windows
application but I wonder if at a high
level if does it look like a typical web
application with a web server and a
database and that sort of thing yeah
it's very much like your typical
software application when I started was
client server but these days a lot more
web based systems I work with but it's a
typical you got database some Services
running in the background and then you
have a UI to do the configuration of the
system and to monitor it and in terms of
the database is that the typical
relational database like a SQL Server a
postgress that kind of thing correct
yeah SQL Server is typically I've seen
Oracle for a while I see less Oracle
these days but SQL Server because it's
Windows based in Microsoft Technologies
but yeah there's some other open- source
databases I've seen with Linux based
systems and so the main part that's
unique I suppose would be The Driver as
you mentioned earlier where the host
system knows how to talk to the panels
Downstream yes and it seems like that
could be anything from vendor
proprietary protocols to HTTP just
whatever the vendor chose when they made
that Hardware yeah it's a wide range you
never know what you're going to get each
one is pretty unique there is no
override in standard between host and
panel but there is recently and I've
been involved with the past few years a
pre widely adopted standard that that
has replaced wegan between the panel and
the reader and that is osdp with osdp
provides a true protocol so with the
weekend days you would have separate w
wires for all the functionality so you
would have a buzzer wire you would have
a LED wire and You' have a different LED
wire for different colors it was very
cumbersome since like I said there was
no protocol involved with wean OSP
provides a encrypted protocol between
the reader and the panel and it's an
open standard I'm actually involved with
validating that devices are properly
implemented and can be compatible so
it's no longer I have to buy this reader
with this panel you can buy any OSP
compliant reader and hook it up to your
OSP client panel and they should operate
you know be able to plug and play them
in like you would do with a USB device
to your computer you would plug it in
and start communicating and being able
to get card reads and make beep and
sounds and flashlights when you grant
access to green things of that nature
and this is starting to become widely
adopted it like I said it takes time
because you have to replace devices you
can't just add the new standard to your
software and push a button you have to
update all the hardware to do that so
one of the things I did I think that
helped to drive adoption is I provided
all the code through open source
repository so it made it real easy for
vendors to be able to do test and
implement the OSP standard they didn't
have to rebuild everything from scratch
they had reference implementations and
I'm hoping that that can be replicated
throughout these different layers so now
we have the OSP standard replacing weend
I talked about earlier there's some
standards hopefully one of them will be
widely adopted to provide communication
between the credential and the reader
that doesn't have the vulnerabilities
that we've discussed earlier uses pki
and the one I'm involved right now is
called peacock it's a public key open
credential that uses public key for
authorization of the credential and
doesn't share the private key so those
two areas are coming along really well
and then you know still the panel
between the panel and the host that's
still mostly proprietary there is an
open standard out there but hasn't been
widely adopted called EnV and EnV if
you're involved with video surveillance
is a very popular standard any camera
you buy I don't think you can even buy a
camera these days without oniv support
so that allows cameras to be hooked up
to any video management system and be
able to recognize its capabilities and
download video typically through rtsp
pretty seamlessly and they do have a
profile for physical access control but
I do not believe anybody's really
adopted it so that's one of the things
I'll probably be looking at in the near
future to see do we take the oniv ACT
control profile and create some open
source implementations and hopefully
that will drive some adoptions or is
there make sense to come up with a new
open standard but you kind of have to
take these one at a time and hopefully
get the full interoperable open platform
available you know that is truly secure
and since it's open people are free to
look at it and if there's security
vulnerabilities you know in real time be
able to apply fixes and make comments on
those standards it's easy to say oh our
proprietary solution is secure when no
one looks at it it's easy to make that
claim the nice thing about Open
Standards is everybody can look at it
and comment and raise concerns if there
is a fundamental security vulnerability
with that approach yeah I mean so that's
interesting because it seems like you're
involved in each section you're involved
with card to reader which is that
peacock thing you mentioned and then
reader to panel which is that osdp
standard and then finally you have the
host system to panel which there is that
existing onvif standard but maybe
that'll work out maybe it won't sounds
like yeah exactly yeah and to have a
fully secure system open system all
three of those interconnects need to
have the proper implementation if any of
those are not properly implemented and
secure you know the weakest link in your
chain type situation you could cause
introduce security vulnerabilities into
your system and so if somebody were to
take your osdp library it sounds like
what they would be able to do is when
somebody scans their card at the reader
they would be able to get that card
number they would be able to like you
were saying trigger things or
communicate back to the reader to tell
it to show a green light because the
access is granted or things like that
exactly so I actually regularly hook up
readers directly to my PC using a USB a
serial connector and hook the reader up
and I'm able to connect to it query it
to see who makes the reader and it's a
true protocol so you you can do all the
typical protocol actions and you can you
pull it to make make sure it's actually
online surprisingly the old wegan
readers you wouldn't know if it was
offline until an employee would call the
Operation Center and say you know this
reader is not working and no one would
know because it's just a one-way
communication with OSP has a second
letters s for supervise you can actually
supervise that connection see if it's
online not only if it's online if
someone's trying to tamper with it so if
for some reason there's an actual
command let you know if it was power
cycled or if there was a tamper
someone's trying to mess with the reader
so once you have a true protocol there's
a lot more you can do to secure and get
in and monitor that endpoint that wasn't
available before so once you have that
connected to your computer you can do a
lot of things as far as Diagnostics you
can update firmware anything you would
do that you would hook up to the panel
you could do from your computer I wrote
my open source using net because most of
my clients are using Windows anyway so
net seems and added all the commands and
stuff and I have a little test console
so if you're having and I have other
tools to BAS Bas off of that so if
you're having a reader that just doesn't
seem to be working with your panel you
can hook it up and run some diagnostic
commands you could do a packet trace and
you can actually figure out why it's not
behaving as expected and does that
extend out to the you gave the example
of the most secure credential you could
use would be something that uses pki
that has like a client ser and things
like that would it be from your library
you can actually receive the client SE
yeah so there's been updates to osdp one
reason I'm involved is that validation
of the public key validation can be done
either at the reader or the panel if
it's done at the panel it needs a
protocol to transmit that information
and there's some back and forth in these
AG go you need to get the public key you
need to send some validated data to the
credential and the credential with the
private key will send back some data and
you can validate if it matches as
expected so to do that you need
something like OSP so that's why I'm
involved and I've added extensions to
OSP it's still the standard is still in
draft so I'm still in active development
but you could hook up the reader and
present a peacock credential and use the
library to validate the public private
key pair on that credential you can also
do that validation on the reader and the
reader if it has more intelligence on it
it could do the back and forth challenge
response and it will send back your
standard old school wegan bid array data
but do it within an osdb backet it's for
backward compatibility and because the
panel might not be able to do the well
there's no panels that can do peacock
right now natively so you kind of revert
back to the old B the bit array from the
weekend days and send that back to the
panel but it's in an encrypted ocp
packet so it can't be easily intercepted
or spoof or clone along the wire and I
suppose it's been somewhat implied but I
think when we typically think of
Internet of Things type things we think
of things that have an ethernet port and
connect to a switch but I think
typically these readers and maybe even
some of the panels a lot of them are
using serial communication right so yeah
there's a lot of discussion so the seral
is Legacy stuff it's hard to replace
Legacy stuff and you have to work around
those constraints so when Access Control
really electronic access physical Access
Control took off everything was it was C
prohibitive to put a network port on
every you know these days you know you
can put either netport or Wireless chip
and you know it's dimes or dollars but
back then it could be a significant cost
it could be basically doubling the
reader price to put you know these chips
on so when they first got deployed to a
lot of these places the easiest thing to
do is just do a seral and we're not
talking about high traffic either I mean
we're just talking the common wegan is
just 26 bits you know a few bytes so you
don't need a highspeed ethernet Port you
know the serial Port does just fine and
then there's distance ethernet can I
think go if I remember and I I haven't
been doing it work in a long time but I
think it's like 300 or 400 ft if you
have a panel in the middle of the
building that's not going to reach to
your door your door is going to be maybe
thousands of feet away depending on how
big the building is it's like a
warehouse serial Communications with the
right cable and can uses rs45 can go
thousands of feet I think up to 4,000 ft
so that's in order of magnitude is
longer so instead of putting access
control panels all over your building
you could put a central one and run all
your wires low voltage wires everywhere
and it's much cheaper for those wires
compared to ethernet wires it's just two
pairs it's half duplex uh but just two
wires and power and you can you know you
can set up your door if you had ethernet
you would have ethernet cable and you'd
have an ethernet switch you would have
to get it involved is allocated IP
addresses a lot more complexity so the
rs45 zero communication is a much more
economical and it doesn't really other
than being able to access it from the
internet it doesn't really have too many
downsides at this stage but I would
imagine things could change and you know
ethernet might be something that become
more prevailing as we move forward there
were ethernet readers out over I've seen
ethernet readers but they never really
took off like I said if you're an
installer there's not much to gain by
putting an Ethernet reader on for the
type of traffic and and it just creates
actually more complexity and more
downtime because you have to like I said
you have to hook it up to a switch
depending on the installation if it's a
small business they might have like a
cheap switch they bought at Best Buy and
you know that thing might crap out every
day and people can't get access to the
building so it's good to have everything
kind of self-contained there are
benefits to keeping that self-contained
and have better control over the system
yeah I think that's one of the
interesting things about physical Access
Control is I think with a lot of
software development the physical
locations of things is so abstracted out
like most people don't think about oh
how long an Ethernet run do I need to
have from one device to the other it's
just not something you even think about
but in this space it actually matters so
that's yeah you can't really abstract
out the hardware it's there you have to
think about every time I do software
development physical access control the
hardware is always in the back of your
mind and a lot of discussions I had with
other software developers sometimes you
know we want to do a certain way and our
software development background says
well this makes perfect sense is why
aren't we doing this way and then you
kind of have to reflect and say well it
doesn't work in a hardware environment
with low cost end points like you kind
of have to always take a step back and
think about the impacts of the stuff
you're developing how that's going to be
used in the real world and sometimes it
doesn't line up and you have to adjust
and sometimes not do the most elegant
solution some you know sometimes I I
hate to use the word hack but you have
to find ways around that and be able to
make the best of that situation when
you're dealing with Antiquated Hardware
really if you're a software developer
that always strives for that perfect you
know code base where everything kind of
works elegantly together physical Access
Control would probably drive you crazy
because it's rarely you can do that
because you're always got constraints
and I find that exciting because there's
a certain amount of satisfaction where
you know this is elegant solution to
where you want to go and you have these
constraints it becomes you know every
time I get into a project it's always a
unique situation where you kind of have
to work around these constraints and you
figure out and if you really feel like
you did a good job you're very close to
that elegant solution you really didn't
compromise anything with your design you
everything you want to do is still there
but it still works well in the physical
space and I think that's something that
I always strive for in my development
efforts I think that's a good place to
end it on but is there anything else you
wanted to mention no I think we did a
good run through of all the aspect of
software development within the physo
access control industry I really enjoyed
this discussion that was great if people
want to learn more about your osdp
library or your consultancy where should
they look uh so I have a website it's
z-bit co.com they can go there and I
have some links to some my open source
projects and some information about
things I'm involved with so that's a
good place to start Jonathan thank you
so much for joining me on software
engineering radio great great talking to
you all right this has been Jeremy Jung
for software engineering radio thanks
for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at sr.ntr
[Music]
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at
team-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening